By far, the most common type of cable used in LANs is unshielded twisted-pair cable.
These cables are used for your standard Ethernet networks.
Unshielded twisted-pair cable, or UTP for short, simply has four twisted pairs of wires that run throughout the cable and transmit data.
The pairs of wires are twisted as to help avoid EMI, electromagnetic interference. UTP is inexpensive and easy to install.
For cable that runs through high areas of EMI, such as areas with machinery or fluorescent lighting, you may want to consider STP, shielded twisted-pair cable.
STP has an extra shielding that coats the wires to, again, help avoid EMI. STP is not used as much as UTP for two reasons.
First, it is more expensive than UTP. Secondly, the twisting of pairs of wires in UTP is usually enough to hold off EMI.
One more aspect of twisted-pair cabling you need to know about for the exam is that of plenum cable, which is cable with a plenum jacket.
In most cases, plenum cable is required for cable running through walls or in between floors. The reason? Plenum cable will not give off a noxious odor in case of a fire.
Non-plenum cable will. Thus, it is important to check the labels on twisted-pair cables to make sure you have plenum cable when needed.